today's video is all about making one of the
most luxurious vanilla bean pastes that you
can make much better than any starboard version
it's super simple so let's just get stuck in and
see how easy it [Music] is yeah Staple in the ice
cream world is vanilla extract it's you know used
in everything vanilla beans are often you know
targeted for luxury recipes whatever that means
um and vanilla bean is targeted as that luxury
version because you get the seeds inside so you
get that vanilla bean caviar as it's sometimes
known in your recipes now in vanilla ice cream
which is still one of the top five flavors in
the world it makes a big difference if you buy
this super cheap crap from the supermarket it's a
weird yellow color which is artificial and it has
a very artificial vanilla kind of flavor it's you
know vanilla Essence rather than vanilla extract
you change that to vanilla extract you get a
much more natural vanilla flavor which makes
the difference goes from being store-bought junk
to you know Artisan ice cream you take that jump
again and you go to vanilla beans and you go from
standard Artisan ice cream to luxury Artisan ice
cream the difference being with vanilla bean and
vanilla bean paste is the vanilla bean paste has
the actual Bean itself completely disintegrated
into this mix so you have a lot of beans go into
making vanilla bean paste you have all of that
vanilla flavor which you lose by discarding the
bean it's now in your vanilla bean paste you get
all of the seeds you get all of those black Flex
throughout your ice cream whatever flavor it is
and it's not just reserved for vanilla flavor ice
cream or vanilla flavor whatever it is vanilla is
a flavor booster so it enhances other flavors as
well like salt does so you can use it in Savory
dishes you know much like chocolate chocolate and
coffee coffee boosts the chocolate flavor so next
time you make a hot chocolate or hot cocoa add
1/4 teaspoon of coffee to it and see what it does
you can also if you don't want to do the coffeee
add just a touch of salt that will bring that
chocolate flavor forward put vanilla bean paste
in there just a/4 teaspoon of vanilla bean paste
in a really nice big mug of hot chocolate or hot
cocoa the difference is astounding so with
that in mind how easy actually is it to make
I mean really easy so what are you going to need
let's get all this stuff out of way first things
first you're going to need a sterilized bottle jar
container whatever it is you're going to use just
make sure it's been thoroughly cleaned because
this is going to last years all right vanilla
extract will last Almost indefinitely because it's
made predominantly with alcohol if that's the one
you've gone for if you've gone for a glycerin
version again it will just last forever vanilla
beans do go off but it does take a while much
the same as as a vanilla bean paste you know I
like to store mine in the fridge this is I don't
know version 195 million it's been in the fridge
this came over from the UK it's it's bulletproof
and when you open it up and you smell it it's
incredible it's thick it's luxurious the smell is
out of this world so what do we need stop talking
Jones we need our scale [Music]
so we're going to start with 70 G of vanilla
beans okay now I'll show you what that equates
to 70 G of vanilla beans that is 2 4 6 8 10 12
14 17 vanilla beans these are Grade B I'd say
they're they're not grade A CU there's not a lot
of moisture left in them but they're still plump
enough to mold between your fingers so if you if
you pick up a vanilla bean and it's hard through
and through hard then that's a you know I don't
if there was a grade C I don't know but that's
probably one to avoid cuz there's no moisture
left in your bean so you don't have a lot of that
flavor if you can pick it up between your fingers
and just squeeze it just gently and it gives
enough that it starts to mold within your
fingers you've still got a good amount of
moisture in there okay grade A can be twice as
thick as this but they are incredibly expensive
I mean all vanilla is expensive I already smell
like vanilla that's never a bad thing so we've
got our beans there okay you can half this
quarter this whatever it is you don't need
to make 500 G 500 mlit of vanilla bean paste
I'm just showing you how to do it with our
pan on our scale we need 280 G of water from
the world's worst pouring jug thanks Canadian
Tire 280 G of water and to that we're
going to add in 160 g of [Music]
sugar don't worry if you go over on the sugar
doesn't make any difference it actually will
make it thicker uh it will be a touch sweeter
but it won't be noticeable cuz you're going to
be putting it in other recipes so it will just
make it thicker it will make that sugar syrup
thicker that's what we're creating here now into
that as well we're going to add 50 [Music] g donk
of corn syrup what does a corn syrup do well
when you create a sugar syrup you're going
to the process of creating an invert sugar
invert sugars can recrystallize that that's
a standard thing corn syrup which is a slightly
different mix of glucose and fructose will stop
that recrystallization or it will slow it down
um if something like honey crystallizes in the
jar that's kind of what's Happening that
the the sugar crystals are just forming
those bonds again you heat it up and it
it dissipates honey is a natural source
of glucose and fructose honey is like a dirty
invert sugar I mean it's not you know dirty it
it's just got other stuff in it natural stuff
but that's what it is it's an invert sugar
so we've got our water our sugar and our corn
syrup in here we're going to get this on a hub
and just tick this over at a medium low heat
and whilst we're doing that we'll get rid of
this we need to chop our vanilla beans today is
a morning where I've made blueberry ice cream
protein ice cream vanilla bean paste all
in one morning so there's stuff everywhere
so we're going to chop these up I personally
like to cut the end off of the vanilla beans
purely because that can sometimes be
quite hard and doesn't blend up very
well like so and now we've got our straight
beans get a small knife we want to split
these so we've got our vanilla beans split
in half we're now just going to chop them
up into relatively small pieces these are
kind of you know 5 mm something like that
you know there we go chopped up all these
little black flecks are the vanilla seeds
so we don't really want to waste those
now we're going to just take our pan back off the
heat and we're going to give it a little bit of a
stir we're going to put our chopped vanilla beans
in our syrup quick Stir of that it's going
to go back on the heat now that Medium low
heat and we're just going to let it tick over
over until we've reduced it down to a thick
[Music] syrup this was cooking down for
about 45 minutes super low just enough
so that it's got some you know bubbling
on the top and it's starting to just cool
down which means it's thickening up a bit so
what we're going to do is we're going to get
our things ready you can use either whatever
container you've got you know we got a bottle
we've got a kill in a jar I'm going to use
the jar and you want a blender of some kind
or food processor cuz what we're going to
do is blit this in our food processor so
you need to make sure that this is cooled down
enough cuz you need to put it in here [Music]
strain it
through make sure you push through any
remaining liquid out of your beans right
I'm not as you know from this channel I not
afraid of showing things that go wrong this
little kitchen Ed mixer was apparently got the
capacity to deal with this it doesn't the heat
from the mix that was maintained as it was being
Blended up increased the amount of air which then
pushed it out the top etc etc etc but what we
are left with here is a gloriously dark let me
give you a little close-up shot a gloriously
dark oh come on there we go vanilla bean paste
and man everything's making a noise today
and we are going to pour that in here
and don't waste all this get that out get those
seeds in there as well just like that and there
we have a vanilla bean paste it it will stiffen
in the refrigerator so in that goes there's enough
vanilla bean paste there for a good long while
there we go ex vanilla explosions and everything
it's surprisingly easy to make that if you got a
big food processor that's perfect for doing this
because it will deal with this size no problems
at all you could probably use a blender you know
like a smoothie blender as well you you just
need to leave it going for a good while and
that's pretty much it you don't have to
waste this either this is the remnants
of the vanilla beans you can dry that out back
in the oven and then you can put that in other
food as well don't waste all of this stuff
you can pretty much use everything that's
come out of this process so in the fridge this
goes and vanilla bean paste for you hopefully
you enjoyed this random little touch and
vanilla explosion that occurred thanks
very much for watching don't forget to like
And subscribe I'll see you next time [Music]